A Guide to the Papers of Miss Roy Land, 1943-1976
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Miss Roy Land 1943-1976
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12727
This collection consists of ca. 3000 items (3 shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift from Roy Land of Charlottesville, Virginia, in July 1977.
Biographical/Historical Information
Returah Royster Land was born in Henry County, Virginia, March 13, 1908. In 1925 she received a B.S. degree from Averett College, Danville, Virginia, and taught high school English in Spencer, Virginia, until 1929. She then attended the University of Virginia where she studied education at the undergraduate level and received a M.S. degree in English in 1931. In the same year her career as circulation librarian started at the University of Virginia, first in the original library in the Rotunda and then at the new Alderman Library after 1938. Roy Land held the faculty position as director of Circulation Services until her retirement in 1977. During this time, she was away from Charlottesville for only two years: in 1943 she attended the University of Michigan and received a B.S. in library science, and in 1959 she served as a library consultant in Hong Kong and Formosa.
Roy Land was always active during her forty-seven years with the University, both with the library and with outside interests. She was a charter member of the Virginia Players in 1929 and worked with them as both an actress and a director. She also served on many professional committees in various capacities, particularly within the American Library Association, the Southeastern Library Association, and the Virginia Library Association. Her interest in Charlottesville went beyond the university as well. She served on the Charlottesville Public Library Board and the Board of the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Unitarian Church.
Scope and Content Information
The Roy Land Papers consist of ca. 3000 items (3 shelf feet), 1943-1976, during which time Roy Land served as director of Circulation Services for the University of Virginia Library. The papers include correspondence and printed matter concerning Alderman Library and correspondence, reports, minutes, and miscellaneous printed matter resulting from Roy Land's membership and committee activities within various professional organizations that activities within various professional organizations that included the American Library Association (A.L.A.), Southeastern Research Libraries (A.S.E. R. L.), and Virginia Library Association (V.L.A.). There are also some papers dealing with Charlottesville organizations such as the Charlottesville Public Library Board, Lychnos Society (U. Va. Women's scholastic honor society), and the American Association of University Women (A.A.U.W.).
Organization
These papers are organized according to the association or group involved. These groups are separated into three main categories:
1. Papers concerned with Alderman Library and the University
2. Papers dealing with organizations of the city of Charlottesville
3. Professional library organizations.
Contents List
- Material re the University of Virginia and Alderman Library (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: General 1946-1976, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Gift Fund: Correspondence and Book Lists 1957, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Legislation: Public Library Services Bill 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Savage, Louise: Obituary Information 1964 (Box 1)
  - Student Library Committee: Correspondence 1957-1967 (Box 1)
  - Student Library Committee: Minutes, Membership Lists, Invoices, and Misc. 1959-1968 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1949-1973 (Box 1)
- Material re Charlottesville, Va. Organizations
  - American Association of University Women: letter, speech, and printed matter 1955-1975 (Box 1)
  - Lychonos Society: Correspondence and membership lists 1953-1976 (Box 1)
  - McIntire Public Library: General Correspondence 1958-1964 (Box 1)
  - McIntire Library: - Friends of: Printed news letter 1964, 1975 (Box 1)
  - McIntire Public Library: Notes, Minutes, Reports 1958-1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - McIntire Public Library: Miscellaneous Printed Matter 1958-1968, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Unitarian Church: Sermons and Bulletins 1958-197, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Material re Professional Library Organizations
  - Virginia Library Association
    - Correspondence: General 1948-1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence re: Roy Land's term as President 1956 (Box 2)
    - Activities Committee: Correspondence 1949-1963, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Activities Committee: Memos, Agenda, and Minutes 1956-1964 (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee: Memos, Agenda, and Minutes 1956-1964 (Box 2)
    - Nominating Committee: Correspondence 1957-1963 (Box 2)
    - Memos and Organizational Materials 1949-1960 (Box 2)
    - Minutes and Conference Information 1951-1964 (Box 2)
    - Principal Report 1957-1963 (Box 3)
    - Reports on ALA conference by VLA representative 1962-1964 (Box 3)
    - Virginia Library Statistics 1946-1958 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1954-1964 (Box 3)
  - Southeastern Library Association
    - General Information 1960, 1973, n.d. (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1948-1968, 1972, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence re: Defense and Federal Relations Committee 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Executive Board and Workshop: Minutes and Membership list 1956-1965 (Box 4)
    - Membership Committee: Memos and Membership lists 1958-1973 (Box 4)
    - Memos and Agenda 1955-1960 (Box 4)
    - Minutes and Conference Programs 1958-1960 (Box 4)
    - Programs and Newsletters 1946-1958 (Box 4)
    - Proposals re: "Life Membership: n.d. (Box 4)
    - Reports of Committee 1953 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1950-1956, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Association of Southeastern Research Libraries
    - Conference Information and Printed Matter 1958, 1966, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Newsletter and General Information 1958-1966; 1973 (Box 4)
    - Memos 1958, 1965 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Projects 1961-1965 (Box 4)
    - Southeastern Regional Commission On Research Library Cooperation: Newsletter 1958 Feb. (Box 4)
    - Southern Humanities Conference: Minutes, Programs, and Miscellaneous 1950-1951 (Box 4)
  - American Library Association
    - General Information 1958-1975 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence: General 1955-1968 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Newsletter re Intellectual Freedom 1956, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Activities Committee: Final Report On New Directions for ALA 1970 June (Box 4)
    - Association of College and Research Libraries: Brochure Designs n.d. (Box 4)
    - Circulation Control Committee: Correspondence 1962-1964 (Box 4)
    - Circulation Control Committee: Printed Reports 1963, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Circulation Services Section: Correspondence 1959-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Circulation Services Section: Miscellaneous 1961-1970 (Box 5)
    - Constitution and By-laws 1953-1963 (Box 5)
    - Conference: San Francisco, Ca-Correspondence and Printed Material 1947 (Box 5)
    - Conference: Miami, F1 - Program 1949 (Box 5)
    - Conference: Chicago, I1-Reports, Proposals, Miscellaneous 1972 (Box 5)
    - Copyright Information: Correspondence, Reports, and Minutes 1963-1972 (Box 5)
    - Council: Correspondence and Reports 1960-1965 (Box 5)
    - Executive Board: Miscellaneous 1963 (Box 5)
    - Library of Congress: Report re Bryant Memo 1962 (Box 5)
    - Library Technology Program: Correspondence, Minutes, Miscellaneous 1971 (Box 5)
    - Library Technology Program: Correspondence re book-binding project 1964-1970 (Box 5)
    - Membership Committee: Correspondence 1947-1965, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Membership Committee: Minutes, Information, List of Members, etc. 1953-1957, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Membership Promotional Material 1953-1963 (Box 6)
    - Report re Demobilization and the Library 1943 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1958-1964 (Box 6)